<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:lang="en">
    <title>Sequence alignment in XSLT 3.0</title>
    <info>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>David</firstname>
                <othername>J.</othername>
                <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>David J. Birnbaum is Professor of Slavic Languages and Literatures at the
                    University of Pittsburgh. He has been involved in the study of electronic text
                    technology since the mid-1980s, has delivered presentations at a variety of
                    electronic text technology conferences, and has served on the board of the
                    Association for Computers and the Humanities, the editorial board of
                        <citetitle>Markup languages: theory and practice</citetitle>, the advisory
                    board of <emphasis>Balisage: the markup conference</emphasis>, and the Text
                    Encoding Initiative Technical Council. Much of his electronic text work
                    intersects with his research in medieval Slavic manuscript studies, but he also
                    often writes about issues in the philosophy of markup.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Professor</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, University of Pittsburgh
                    (US)</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>djbpitt@gmail.com</email>
            <uri>http://www.obdurodon.org</uri>
        </author>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>sequence alignment</keyword>
            <keyword>xslt</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <abstract>
            <para>The Needleman Wunsch algorithm, which this year enjoys its quinquagenary
                anniversary, has been proven to produce an optimal global pairwise sequence
                alignment. Because this dynamic programming algorithm requires the updating of
                variables, it has posed challenges for functional programming paradigms like the one
                underlying XSLT. The present report explores these challenges and provides an
                implementation of the Needleman Wunsch algorithm in XSLT 3.0.</para>
        </abstract>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <section>
            <title>Why sequence aligment matters</title>
            <para>Sequence alignment is a way of identifying and modeling similarities and
                differences in sequences of items, and has proven insightful and productive in both
                the natural sciences (especially in biology and medicine, where it is applied to
                genetic sequences) and the humanities (especially in text-critical scholarship,
                where it is applied to sequences of words in variant versions of a text). In textual
                scholarship, which is the domain in which the present report was developed, sequence
                alignment assists the philologist in identifying locations where the witnesses agree
                and where they disagree.<note>
                    <para><emphasis>Witness</emphasis>, sometimes expanded as <emphasis>manuscript
                            witness</emphasis>, is a technical term in text-critical scholarship for
                        a manuscript that provides evidence of the history of a text.</para>
                </note> These moments of agreement and disagreement, in turn, provide evidence about
                probable (or, at least, candidate) moments of shared transmission between textual
                witnesses, and thus serve as evidence to construct and support a philological
                argument about the history of a text.<note>
                    <para>For an introduction to, among other things, the evaluation of shared
                        readings as a component of textual criticism see <xref
                            linkend="trovato_2014"/>.</para>
                </note></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Biological and textual alignment</title>
            <para>Insofar as biomedical research enjoys a larger scientific community and richer
                funding resources than textual humanities scholarship, it is not surprising that the
                literature, and the science reported in that literature, is quantitatively greater
                in the natural sciences than in the humanities. Furthermore, insofar as all sequence
                alignment is similar in certain ways, it is both necessary and appropriate for
                textual scholars to seek opportunities to adapt biomedical methods for their own
                purposes. For those reasons, the present report focuses ona a method first proposed
                in a biological context and later also applied in philology.</para>
            <para>Although this report does not take account of differences in the size and scale of
                biological and philological data, it is nonetheless the case that alignment problems
                in biomedical contexts, on the one hand, and in textual contexts, on the other,
                typically differ at least in the following ways: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Genetic alignment may operate at sequence lengths involving entire
                            chromosomes or entire genomes, which is orders of magnitude larger than
                            the largest real-world textual alignment task.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Genetic alignment operates with a vocabulary of four words (nucleotide
                            bases), while textual alignment often involves a vocabulary of hundreds
                            or thousands of different words.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>The preceding systematic differences in size and scale invite questions about
                whether the different shape of the source data in the two domains might invite
                different methods. Especially in the case of heuristic approaches that are not
                guaranteed to produce an optimal solution, is it possible that compromises required
                to make data at large scale computationally tractable might profitably be avoided in
                domains involving data ot a substantially smaller scale? Although the present rather
                specific report does not seek to engage with this question, it remains part of the
                context within which solutions to alignment tasks in different disciplines
                ultimately should be assessed.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Global pairwise alignment</title>
            <para>The following two distinctions—not between biological and textual alignment, but
                within both domains—are also relevant:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Both genetic and textual alignment tasks can be divided into
                                <emphasis>global</emphasis> and <emphasis>local</emphasis>
                            alignment. The goal of global alignment is to find the best alignment of
                            all items in the entire sequences. In textual scholarship this is often
                            called <emphasis>collation</emphasis> (cf. e.g., <xref
                                linkend="fv_reader"/>). The goal of local alignment is to find
                            moment where subsequences correspond, without attempting to optimize the
                            alignment of the entire sequences. A common textual use for local
                            alignment is <emphasis>text reuse</emphasis>, e.g., finding moments
                            where Dante quotes or paraphrases Ovid (cf. <xref
                                linkend="peteghhem_2015"/>, <xref linkend="intertextual_dante"
                            />).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Both genetic and textual alignment tasks may involve
                                <emphasis>pairwise alignment</emphasis> or <emphasis>multiple
                                alignment</emphasis>. Pairwise alignment refers to the alignment of
                            two sequences; multiple alignment refers to the alignment of more than
                            two sequences. In textual scholarship multiple alignment is often called
                                <emphasis>multiple-witness alignment</emphasis>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>The Needleman Wunsch algorithm described and implemented below has been proven to
                identify all optimal global, pairwise alignments of two sequences, and it is
                especially well suited to alignment tasks where the two texts are of comparable size
                and are substantially similar to each other. The present report does not address
                either local alignment or multiple (witness) alignment.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>This report begins by introducing the use of dynamic programming methods within
                the Needleman Wunsch algorithm to identify all optimal global alignments of two
                manuscript witnesses. It then identifies challenges to implementing this algorithm
                in XSLT and discusses those challenges in the context of developing such an
                implementation. All original code discussed here in this report is available at
                    <link xl:href="https://github.com/djbpitt/xstuff/tree/master/nw"/>.</para>
            <para>It should be noted that the goal of this report, and the code it contains, is to
                explore global pairwise sequence alignment in an XSLT environment. For that reason,
                it is not intended that this code function as a stand-alone end-user textual
                collation tool. There are two reasons for specifying the goals and non-goals of the
                present report in this way: <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Textual collation as a philological method involves more than just
                            alignment. For example, the Gothenburg model of textual collation, which
                            has been implemented in the CollateX [<xref linkend="collatex"/>] and
                            Juxta [<xref linkend="juxta"/>] tools, expresses the collation process
                            as a five-step pipeline, within which alignment serves as the third step.<note>
                                <para>For further information about the Gothenburg model see <xref
                                        linkend="gothenburg"/>.</para>
                            </note></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Real-world textual alignment tasks often involve more than two
                            witnesses, that is, they involve multiple-witness, rather than pairwise,
                            alignment. While some approaches to multiple-witness alignment are
                            implemented as a progressive or iterative application of pairwise
                            alignment, these methods are subject to arder effects. Ultimataly,
                            multiple-witness alignment is an NP hard problem with which the present
                            report does not seek to engage.<note>
                                <para><xref linkend="msa"/> provides an overview of multiple
                                    sequence alignment, the term in bioinformatics for what
                                    philologists refer to as multiple-witness alignment.</para>
                            </note></para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>About sequence alignment</title>
        <section>
            <title>Alignments and scoring</title>
            <para>An optimal alignment can be defined as an alignment that yields the best
                    <emphasis>score</emphasis>, where the researcher is responsible for identifying
                an appropriate scoring method. Alignments are of three possible types:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The items from both sequences are aligned and are the same. This is
                            called a <emphasis>match</emphasis>. If the sequences are identical, all
                            item-level alignments are matches.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The items from both sequences are aligned are are different. This is
                            called a <emphasis>mismatch</emphasis>. Mismatches may arise in
                            situations where they are sandwiched between matches. For example, in
                            the sequences <quote>The brown koala</quote> and <quote>The gray
                                koala</quote>, after aligning the words <quote>The</quote> and
                                <quote>koala</quote> in the two sequences (both alignments are
                            matches), the color words sandwiched between them form an aligned
                            mismatch.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An item in one sequence has no corresponding item in the other
                            sequence. This is called a <emphasis>gap</emphasis> or an
                                <emphasis>indel</emphasis> (a correspondence of an item to no item
                            that can be interpreted as either an insertion in one sequence or a
                            deletion from the other). Gaps are inevitable where the sequences are of
                            different lengths, so that, for example. given <quote>The gray
                                koala</quote> and <quote>The koala</quote>, the item
                                <quote>gray</quote> in the first sequence corresponds to a gap in
                            the second. Gaps may also occur with sequences of the same length; for
                            example, if we align <quote>The gray koala lives in Australia</quote>
                            with <quote>The koala lives in South Australia</quote>, both sequences
                            contain six words, but one possible gappy alignment is: <table>
                                <title>Alignment example with gaps</title>
                                <tgroup cols="7">
                                    <tbody>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry>The</entry>
                                            <entry>gray</entry>
                                            <entry>koala</entry>
                                            <entry>lives</entry>
                                            <entry>in</entry>
                                            <entry> </entry>
                                            <entry>Australia</entry>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <entry>The</entry>
                                            <entry> </entry>
                                            <entry>koala</entry>
                                            <entry>lives</entry>
                                            <entry>in</entry>
                                            <entry>South</entry>
                                            <entry>Australia</entry>
                                        </row>
                                    </tbody>
                                </tgroup>
                            </table>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            <para>A common scoring method is to assign a value of <quote>1</quote> to matches,
                    <quote>-1</quote> to mismatches, and <quote>-1</quote> to gaps. These values
                prefer alignments with as many matches as possible, and with as few mismatches and
                gaps as possible. But other scoring methods might, for example, assign a greater
                penalty to gaps than to mismatches, or might assign greater penalties to new gaps
                than to continuations of existing gaps (this is called an
                    <emphasis>affine</emphasis> gap penalty).</para>
            <para>The scoring method determines what will be identified as an optimal alignment for
                a circular reason: optimal in this context is defined as the alignment with the best score.<note>
                    <para>As an extreme example of the role of scoring in determining what will be
                        considered an optimal alignment, if the gap penalty is low and the mismatch
                        penalty is extremely high, the system could prefer not to align any items,
                        and to regard the length of the alignment as the sum of the length of the
                        two sequences, with each item aligned with an indel, so that one sequence
                        begins where the other ends. This is obviously not a realistic real-world
                        scoring system, but it illustrates how the identification of an optimal
                        alignment is a function of the scoring system, and not an inherent property
                        of the data independently of scoring decisions.</para>
                </note> This means that selection of an appropriate scoring method in philological
                alignment should reflect the researcher’s theory of the types of correspondences and
                non-correspondences that are meaningful for identifying textual moments to be
                compared. In the examples below we have assigned a score of <quote>1</quote> for
                matches, <quote>-1</quote> for mistmatches, and <quote>-2</quote> for gaps. This
                scoring system prefers mismatches to gaps, and scores gaps in a linear (not affine)
                way.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Sequence alignment algorithms</title>
            <para>A naïve, brute-force approach to sequence alignment would construct all possible
                alignments, score them, and select the ones with the best scores. This method has
                exponential complexity, and therefore is not realistic even for relatively small
                real-world alignment tasks. Alternatives must therefore reduce the computational
                complexity, ideally by reducing the search space to exclude from consideration in
                advance all alignments that <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be optimal. Where this is
                not possible, a <emphasis>heuristic</emphasis> method excludes from consideration in
                advance all alignments that <emphasis>are unlikely to be</emphasis> optimal. Such
                heuristic methods entail a risk of inadvertently excluding an optimal alignment, but
                in the case of some computationally complex processes, the only known
                simplifications are heuristic.</para>
            <para>In the case of global pairwise alignment the Needleman Wunsch algorithm, described
                below, has been proven always to produce an optimal alignment, according to the
                definition of optimal represented by the scoring method applied. Needleman Wunsch is
                an implementation of <emphasis>dynamic programming</emphasis>, and in the following
                two sections we first describe dynamic programming as a paradigm and then explain
                how it is employed in the Needleman Wunsch algorithm. These explanations are
                preparatory to describing the complications dynamic programming poses for XSLT and
                how those can be resolved.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Dynamic programming and the Needleman Wunsch algorithm</title>
        <section>
            <title>Dynamic programming</title>
            <para>Dynamic programming, a paradigm developed by Richard Bellman at the Rand
                Corporation in the early 1950s, makes it possible to express complex coding tasks as
                a combination of smaller, more tractable, overlapping ones. A commonly cited example
                of a task that is amenable to dynamic programming is a computation of a Fibonacci
                number. Insofar as every Fibonacci number beyond the first two can be expressed as a
                function of the two immediately preceding Fibonacci numbers, a naïve top-down
                approach would compute the two preceding values (which requires commputing all of
                their preceding values), and then their preceding values (again), etc. A dynamic
                bottom-up computation, on the other hand, would calculate each smaller number only
                once and then use those values to move up to larger numbers.<note>
                    <para>A top-down dynamic approach would perform all of the recursive computation
                        at the beginning, but <emphasis>memoize</emphasis> (that is, store and
                        index) the result, so that it could be reused, without having to be
                        recomputed, when it was needed at the next level down.</para>
                </note></para>
            <para>Sequence alignment meets both requirements of a problem that is amenable to
                dynamic programming. First, it can be expressed recursively, that is, if the optimal
                alignment of two long sequences can be identified, the optimal alignment of their
                corresponding subsequences can be extracted as a subset of the longer alignment.
                Second, this recursion is overlapping, that is, the solution to a sub-alignment is a
                component of the solution to a longer alignment. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Needleman Wumsch algorithm</title>
            <para>Dynamic programming and Needleman Wunsch. See <xref linkend="snip"/> for a walk-through.<note>
                    <blockquote>
                        <para>We will begin with the scoring system most commonly used when
                            introducing the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm: substitution scores for
                            matched residues and linear gap penalties. Although Needleman and Wunsch
                            already discussed this scoring system in their 1970 article [NW70], the
                            form in which it is now most commonly presented is due to Gotoh [Got82]
                            (who is also responsible for the affine gap penalties version of the
                            algorithm). An alignment algorithm very similar to Needleman-Wunsch, but
                            developed for speech recognition, was also independently described by
                            Vintsyuk in 1968 [Vin68]. Another early author interested in the subject
                            is Sellers [Sel74], who described in 1974 an alignment algorithm
                            minimizing sequence distance rather than maximizing sequence similarity;
                            however Smith and Waterman (two authors famous for the algorithm bearing
                            their name) proved in 1981 that both procedures are equivalent [SWF81].
                            Therefore it is clear that there are many classic papers, often a bit
                            old, describing Needleman-Wunsch and its variants using different
                            mathematical notations. [<xref linkend="boes_2014"/>, 14; pointers are
                            to <xref linkend="needleman_1970"/>, <xref linkend="gotoh_1982"/>, <xref
                                linkend="vintsyuk_1968"/>, <xref linkend="sellers_1974"/>, and <xref
                                linkend="smith_1981"/>]</para>
                    </blockquote>
                </note></para>
            <para>Needleman Wunsch <quote>is an <emphasis>optimal</emphasis> algorithm, which means
                    that it produces the best possible solution with respect to the chosen scoring
                    system. There exists also non-optimal alignment algorithms, most notably the
                    heuristic methods …</quote> [<xref linkend="boes_2014"/>, 13]</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The challenges of dynamic programming and XSLT</title>
        <para>Why XSLT plays poorly with dynamic programming</para>
        <para>Why for-each doesn’t work</para>
        <para>Why recursion breaks</para>
        <para>Iteration to the rescue</para>
        <para>Thinking in XSLT. Simplifyiing assumption: only one best path, even if there are more
            than one.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Inching toward XSLT-idiomatic sequence alignment</title>
        <section>
            <title>A naive approach</title>
            <para>Build the whole grid using iterate, then walk backwards using recursion</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Save yourself a trip</title>
            <para>Record the full path in each cell to avoid having to walk back</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Using the diagonal</title>
            <para>Jeni (<xref linkend="tennison_2007"/>) uses it to reduce recursion; for-each over
                each diagonal, so recur only for new diagonal</para>
            <para>for-each allows parallel processing (<xref linkend="wong_2002"/>, <xref
                    linkend="naveed_2005"/>), although we can’t guarantee it because XSLT doesn’t
                give the programmer explicit control over parallelization (cf. Python). Saxon EE
                supports parallel processing of <tag>xsl:for-each</tag> with the optional <tag
                    class="attribute">@saxon:threads</tag> attribute. [<xref
                    linkend="saxon_for-each"/>]<note>
                    <para><blockquote>
                            <para>Processing using multiple threads can take advantage of multi-core
                                CPUs. However, there is an overhead, in that the results of
                                processing each item in the input need to be buffered. The overhead
                                of coordinating multiple threads is proportionally higher if the
                                per-item processing cost is low, while the overhead of buffering is
                                proportionally higher if the amount of data produced when each item
                                is processed is high. Multi-threading therefore works best when the
                                body of the xsl:for-each instruction performs a large amount of
                                computation but produces a small amount of output.</para>
                        </blockquote> [<xref linkend="saxon_threads"/>]</para>
                </note></para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Conclusions</title>
            <para>Tennison concludes that:</para>
            <para><blockquote>
                    <para>I guess the take-home messages are: (a) try to iterate rather than recurse
                        whenever you can and (b) don’t blindly adapt algorithms designed for
                        procedural programming languages to XSLT. [<xref linkend="tennison_2007"
                        />]</para>
                </blockquote></para>
            <para>The XSLT 3.0 <tag>xsl:iterate</tag> element provides a method to iterate reliably
                that was not available to Tennison in 2007. Beyond that, the implementation above
                extends Tennison’s XSLT-idiomatic implementation of a Levenshtein distance algorithm
                to the closely related domain of Needleman Wunsch sequence alignment, and also
                explores explicitly where XSLT provides functional alternatives to
                    <tag>xsl:iterate</tag> that enable opportunities for parallel execution.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <bibliography xml:id="references">
        <title>Works cited</title>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="bellman_1952" xreflabel="Bellman 1952">Bellman, Richard E. 1952.
                <quote>On the theory of dynamic programming.</quote>
            <citetitle>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</citetitle> 38(8):716–19.
                <link xl:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1063639/"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="bellman_1954" xreflabel="Bellman 1954">Bellman, Richard E. <quote>The
                theory of dynamic programming.</quote> Technical report P-550. Santa Monica: Rand
            Corporation. <link xl:href="http://smo.sogang.ac.kr/doc/bellman.pdf"/></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="boes_2014" xreflabel="Boes 2014">Boes, Olivier. 2014. <quote>Improving
                the Needleman-Wunsch algorithm with the DynaMine predictor.</quote> Master in
            Bioinformatics thesis, Université lire de Bruxelles.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="collatex" xreflabel="CollateX">CollateX—software for collating textual
            sources. <link xl:href="https://collatex.net/"/></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="snip" xreflabel="Snipacademy Global alignment"><quote>Global alignment.
                Needleman-Wunsch.</quote> Chapter 9 of Pairwise alignment, Bioinformatics Lessons at
            your convenience, Snipacademy. <link
                xl:href="https://binf.snipcademy.com/lessons/pairwise-alignment/global-needleman-wunsch"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="gothenburg" xreflabel="Gothenburg model"><quote>The Gothenburg
                model.</quote> Section 1 of the documentation for <xref linkend="collatex"/>. <link
                xl:href="https://collatex.net/doc/#gothenburg-model"/></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="gotoh_1982" xreflabel="Gotoh 1982">Gotoh, Osamu. 1982. <quote>An
                improved algorithm for matching biological sequences.</quote>
            <citetitle>Journal of molecular biology</citetitle> 162(3):705–08.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="intertextual_dante" xreflabel="Intertextual Dante">
            <quote>Intertextual Dante.</quote>
            <link xl:href="https://digitaldante.columbia.edu/intertexual-dante-vanpeteghem/"/>
        </bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="juxta" xreflabel="Juxta">Juxta. <link
                xl:href="https://www.juxtasoftware.org/"/></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="fv_reader" xreflabel="Frankenstein variorum reader"><quote>Mary
                Shelley’s Frankenstein. A digital variorum edition.</quote>
            <link xl:href="http://frankensteinvariorum.library.cmu.edu/viewer/"/>. See also the
            project GitHub repo at <link xl:href="https://github.com/FrankensteinVariorum/"
            />.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="msa" xreflabel="Multiple sequence alignment (Wikipedia)">Multiple
            sequence alignment (Wikipedia). Accessed 2019-11-03. <link
                xl:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_sequence_alignment"/></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="needleman_1970" xreflabel="Needleman and Wunsch 1970">Needleman, Saul
            B. and Christian D. Wunsch. 1970. <quote>A general method applicable to the search for
                similarities in the amino acid sequence of two proteins.</quote>
            <citetitle>Journal of molecular biology</citetitle> 48 (3): 443–53.
            doi:10.1016/0022-2836(70)90057-4.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="naveed_2005" xreflabel="Naveed et al, 2005">Naveed, Tahir,Imitaz Saeed
            Siddiqui, Shaftab Ahmed. 2005. <quote>Parallel Needleman-Wunsch algorithm for
                grid.</quote> Proceedings of the PAK-US International Symposium on High Capacity
            Optical Networks and Enabling Technologies (HONET 2005), Islamabad, Pakistan, Dec 19–21,
            2005. <link
                xl:href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/c/c4/ParallelNeedlemanAlgorithm.pdf"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="sankoff_1972" xreflabel="Sankoff 1972">Sankoff David. 1972.
                <quote>Matching sequences under deletion/insertion constraints.</quote>
            <citetitle>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the USA</citetitle> 69
            (1): 4–6. doi:10.1073/pnas.69.1.4. <link
                xl:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC427531/pdf/pnas00127-0010.pdf"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="saxon_for-each" xreflabel="Saxon xsl:for-each">Saxon documentation of
                <emphasis>xsl:for-each</emphasis>. <link
                xl:href="https://www.saxonica.com/html/documentation/xsl-elements/for-each.html"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="saxon_threads" xreflabel="Saxon saxon:threads">Saxon documentation of
                <emphasis>saxon:threads</emphasis>. <link
                xl:href="https://www.saxonica.com/html/documentation/extensions/attributes/threads.html"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="sellers_1974" xreflabel="Sellers 1974">Sellers, Peter H. 1974.
                <quote>On the theory and computation of evolutionary distances.</quote>
            <citetitle>SIAM journal on applied mathematics</citetitle> 26(4):787–93.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="smith_1981" xreflabel="Smith et al. 1981">Smith, Temple F., Michael S.
            Waterman, and Walter M. Fitch. 1981. <quote>Comparative biosequence metrics.</quote>
            <citetitle>Journal of molecular evolution</citetitle>, 18(1):38–46.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="tennison_2007" xreflabel="Tennison 2007">Tennison, Jeni. 2007.
                <quote>Levenshtein distance on the diagonal</quote> Posted to <citetitle>Jeni’s
                musings</citetitle>, 2007-05-06. <link
                xl:href="https://www.jenitennison.com/2007/05/06/levenshtein-distance-on-the-diagonal.html"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="trovato_2014" xreflabel="Trovato 2014">Trovato, Paolo.
                <citetitle>Everything you always wanted to know about Lachmann’s method. A
                non-standard handbook of genealogical textual criticism in the age of
                post-structuralism, cladistics, and copy-text.</citetitle> Padova:
            libreriauniversitaria.it , 2014</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="peteghhem_2015" xreflabel="Van Peteghem 2015">Van Peteghem, Julie.
            2015. <quote>Digital readers of allusive texts: Ovidian intertextuality in the Commedia
                and the Digital concordance on intertextual Dante.</quote>
            <citetitle>Humanist studies &amp; the digital age</citetitle>, 4.1, 39–59. DOI:
            10.5399/uo/hsda.4.1.3584. <link
                xl:href="http://journals.oregondigital.org/index.php/hsda/article/view/3584"
            /></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="vintsyuk_1968" xreflabel="Vintsyuk 1968">Vintsyuk, T[aras] K[lymovych].
            1968. <quote>Speech discrimination by dynamic programming.</quote>
            <citetitle>Cybernetics</citetitle> 4(1):52–57.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="wong_2002" xreflabel="Wong 2002">Wang, Bin. 2002. <quote>Implementation
                of a dynamic programming algorithm for DNA sequence alignment on the cell matrix
                architecture. MA thesis, Utah State University.</quote>
            <link xl:href="https://www.cellmatrix.com/entryway/products/pub/wang2002.pdf"
            /></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
</article>
