<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "../../DTD/balisage-1-3.dtd">
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.3"
  xml:id="HR-23632987-8973">
  <title>Raleigh's Discoveries in the New World</title>
  <subtitle>The lure of vegetable culture</subtitle>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>In 1584, Queen Elizabeth I charged Sir Walter Raleigh to discover and colonize lands in
        the New World on behalf of England. This article discusses the efforts and expeditions
        organized under Raleigh's patronage to found a colony in the current-day North Carolina.
        Going beyond the chronological history of the doomed Roanoke colony, the author provides
        insights into relations between the colonists and their native counterparts, discusses the
        botanical riches of the region, and argues that Raleigh's efforts did not end in failure, as
        commonly might be thought.</para>
    </abstract>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Tonia</firstname>
        <othername>Renae</othername>
        <surname>Gaillard</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para>A native of Eleajora, Dr. Gaillard completed her post-graduate studies in Colonial
          American History in 2033. Following these studies, she became an Associate Professor at
          DeBare State University before joining Quetrane University’s faculty. She has chaired the
          university’s Department of History since 2048.</para>
        <para>Dr. Gaillard’s extensive writings include <quote>The Politics Underlying the Salem
            Witch Trials</quote>, <quote>Williamsburg’s Role in the Revolution</quote>,<emphasis
            role="ital">Benjamin Franklin: Scientist, Inventor, and Politician</emphasis>, and
            <emphasis role="ital">Native American Culture and the "True Faith."</emphasis> She is
          currently working on a biography of Simon Kenton, whose role in pioneering Kentucky has
          been overshadowed by fellow backwoodsman Daniel Boone.</para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle>Department Chair</jobtitle>
        <orgname>Quetrane University</orgname>
      </affiliation>
      <email>tgaillard@quetrane.hist.edu</email>
    </author>
    <keywordset role="author">
      <keyword>New World discoveries</keyword>
      <keyword>American colonial history</keyword>
      <keyword>English 16th century history</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>On March 25, 1584, Queen Elizabeth I of England charged Sir Walter Raleigh to<blockquote>
        <para>discover, search, find out, and view such remote, heathen and barbarous lands,
          countries, and territories, not actually possessed of any Christian Prince, nor inhabited
          by Christian People</para>
      <attribution><xref linkend="thorpe97"/></attribution>
      </blockquote> That same year Raleigh sent two captains, Philip Amades and Arthur Barlowe, from
      England to Hispaniola and the Canary Islands; from there, the captains were instructed to
      scout the lands northeast of those already claimed by Spain, to wit, Florida. This land — now
      encompassing the Carolinas and Virginia — was claimed on behalf of England and named
        <quote>Virginia,</quote> in honor of the <quote>Virgin Queen.</quote></para>
    <para>Information processing, especially text markup, was primitive in the colony. For example,
      most text stores were in XML! Documents may have looked like this:
      <programlisting>&lt;teiHeader&gt;
  &lt;fileDesc&gt;
    &lt;titleStmt&gt;
      &lt;title&gt;Farming in the New World&lt;/title&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/titleStmt&gt;
  &lt;/fileDesc&gt;
&lt;/teiHeader&gt;</programlisting>
      Notice the paired Tags: <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;/title&gt;</code> and the
      primitive use of indenting. Unusual features of the colonists data processing practices included:<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Tags</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Meaningful descriptions of the information enclosed by the markers</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Balance</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>All markup is both opened and closed (or explicitly empty)</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Securing a Permanent Colony in the Claimed Lands</title>
    <para>With land claimed in the New World, an expedition was mounted to establish a settlement.
      The first expedition failed. Led by Sir Richard Grenville in April 1585, it encompassed 600
      men of which 105 remained in the colony while Grenville returned to England for additional
      provisions. (<emphasis role="ital">See</emphasis>
      <xref linkend="mul83"/>.) However, when almost a year passed without Grenville’s return, the
      remainder of the expeditionary force took advantage of Sir Francis Drake’s arrival to seek
      return passage to England. <footnote xml:id="mul74">
        <para>It has been argued that the first expedition was not a failure. Richard Grenville did
          return to the colony with additional provisions not long after Drake’s departure, and he
          ordered 15 men, supposedly supplied for two years, to remain in the colony while he
          returned for new settlers. However, it is unknown whether these men were present to greet
          the subsequent expedition.</para>
      </footnote>
    </para>
    <para>The second expedition, organized by John White in 1587, fared better. It sailed with seven
      ships filled with Devon families intent upon establishing a colony in that part of Virginia
      called Roanoke, a word deriving from the speech of native peoples. [<xref linkend="mul88"/>]
      Two years after founding the <quote>Cittie of Raleigh,</quote> houses had been built for
      almost all families residing in the colony, and the colony had celebrated the birth of its
      first children born in the New World. The first child, grandchild of John White and child of
      Ananias and Eleanor Dare, was been named Virginia in honor of the sovereign.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Native Plants and Wildlife</title>
      <para>The European settlers found the New World abundant with commodities <quote>known to
          yield victual and sustenance of man’s life</quote>. The first expeditionary force noted
        that a great variety of berries grew wildly, including raspberries, blueberries, and
        strawberries. Along with maize, native grain, which could be made into bread, grew in the
        area. Two other plants — more properly called roots — which could be saved for winter
        consumption were <quote>cassida</quote> and <quote>chyna.</quote> The settlers discovered
        that while some roots could be eaten much in appearance as they were dug, others had to be
        boiled before use as a foodstuff. As more fully described below, other plants included
        beans, and several crops previously unknown to the Europeans: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><quote>macocqwer</quote> (gourds),</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><quote>melden</quote> (an herb),</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><quote>planta solis</quote> (sunflower — used in a type of bread, as well as for
              broth),</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>peas (powdered in a mortar), and</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>potatoes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Gourds</title>
        <para>The native people grew a variety of large broad-leafed, ground-covering vines which
          produced what they called <quote>macocqwer</quote> or gourds. (<emphasis role="ital"
            >See</emphasis>
          <xref linkend="gourds"/>.) Varying in color among shades of green, yellow, and orange,
          these gourds served a number of functions, not chief of which was as a food source. There
          were two distinct types, soft-shelled and hard-shelled. Of particular interest to the
          settlers were pumpkins; grown throughout the summer, this gourd remained in the fields
          until late autumn’s frost. Following harvest, the gourd could be stored throughout the
          winter and its flesh made into stews.</para>
        <figure xml:id="gourds">
          <title>Gourds</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="jpg" fileref="19450212-2.jpg" width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>While gourds, pumpkins and squashes were new to the English, they were soon
              discovered to be very useful for warding off starvation.</para>
          </caption>
        </figure>
        <para>However, far more important was the hard-skinned gourd. The value of this gourd lay
          not in its potential as a food source, but rather as a container and serving vessel. Once
          dried, these gourds were cut and hollowed for use as storage containers, as well as for
          bowls, ladles, cups, and other types of serving utensils. Indeed, since gourds grew in a
          variety of shapes and sizes, particular gourds could be selected for their resemblance to
          the items sought. For the adventurous, the durable objects could be carved and decorated
          with plant dyes.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Tomatoes</title>
        <para>Also new to the colonists was the tomato. (<emphasis role="ital">See</emphasis>
          <xref linkend="Tomatoes"/>.) Tomatoes were described as thin-skinned succulent fruits with
          pulpy interiors. Almost <quote>Bristol red</quote> in color, the fruit was somewhat round
          in form and the size of a chicken’s egg — not anything approaching the size of modern,
          cultivated varieties. Of particular importance was the plant’s fecundity. The flowering,
          bush-like plant bore fruit over a period of months. Thus, a plant could produce as many as
          15 tomatoes at a given time.</para>
        <figure xml:id="Tomatoes">
          <title>Tomatoes</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata format="jpg" fileref="19450212-1.jpg" width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <caption>
            <para>Tomatoes were among the new fruits discovered in the New World.</para>
          </caption>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Potatoes</title>
        <para>Another root that proved beneficial was the potato. Similarly, to the
            <quote>cassida</quote> mentioned earlier, potatoes were considered roots rather than
          plants, as the edible portion of the plant lay underground. Given the curious nature of
          this legume, several examples were brought back from the New World. In fact, Raleigh
          attempted to cultivate the potato at his estate, Youghall, in Ireland.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Fruits and Nuts</title>
        <para>The colony abounded with a wealth of fruits and nuts, some not previously known to the
          Europeans. In addition to mulberries, strawberries, and blueberries already mentioned, one
          of the more curious fruits found was called <quote>medlar</quote> by the natives. Medlar
          was a fruit not unlike cherries in size and color, but with a much sweeter taste. An
          equally unusual fruit was <quote>metaqvesvnnaqvk</quote>; notwithstanding its red fruit,
          that plant’s more important feature lay in the cochinile insects which fed upon its
          prickly thick leaves <footnote xml:id="mul90">
            <para>In the 16th century, such insects were prized in the making of a vibrant red
              dye.</para>
          </footnote>.</para>
        <para>Equally abundant in variety and size were nuts. In addition to chestnuts and walnuts,
          the natives <quote>harvested</quote> no less than five types of <quote>acorns</quote>.
          These somewhat small nuts were either dried in a manner similar to that used in England
          for malt, or were boiled for broth.</para>
        <table>
          <caption>
            <para>North American Native Plants</para>
          </caption>
          <col align="right" valign="top"/>
          <col valign="top"/>
          <col align="center" valign="top"/>
          <thead>
            <tr valign="top">
              <th>Use</th>
              <th>Plant Part</th>
              <th>Examples</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="8"><emphasis role="bold">Vegetables</emphasis></td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="2">Seeds</td>
              <td>Corn</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Beans</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="3">Fruits</td>
              <td>Squash</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Peppers</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Tomatoes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="2">Roots</td>
              <td>Potatoes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Sweet Potatoes</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="4"><emphasis role="bold">Teas</emphasis></td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td rowspan="2">Leaves</td>
              <td>Mountain Mint (Namewuskons)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Dawn Mint (Wabinowusk)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr valign="top">
              <td>Berries</td>
              <td>Wintergreen</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <appendix xml:id="mul83">
    <title>The First Expeditionary Force’s Colony, 1585-1586 <footnote xml:id="mul5">
        <para>This Appendix contains an actual list of the individuals who sailed to the Roanoke
          Colony in 1585. (<emphasis role="ital">See</emphasis>
          <citation>Durant, David N., <quote>Raleigh’s Lost Colony</quote>, Appendix I, Atheneum,
            NY: 1981.</citation>)</para>
      </footnote>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Philip Amades, Admirall of the countrie</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Hariot</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Acton</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Edward Stafford</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Luddington</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Marvyn</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Gardyner</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Captaine Vaughan</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Kendall</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Prideox</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Robert Holecroft</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rise Courtney</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Hugh Rogers</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Foxe</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Nugent</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Darby Glande</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Kelle</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Gostigo</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Erasmus Clefs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Ketcheman</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Linsey</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Rottenbury</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Roger Deane</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Harris</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Frauncis Norris</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Matthewe Lyne</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Kettell</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Wisse</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Thomas Harvie</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Snelling</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Anthony Russe</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Allyne</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Master Michel Polyson</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Cage</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Parre</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Randes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Geffrey Churchman</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Farthowe</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Taylor</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Philppe Robyns</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Phillipes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Valentine Beale</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>James Skinner</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>George Eseven</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Chaundeler</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Philip Blunt</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richard Poore</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Robert Yong</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Marmaduke Constable</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Hesket</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Wasse</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Fever</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Daniel</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Taylor</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richard Humfrey</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Wright</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Gabriell North</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Robert Biscombe</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Backhouse</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William White</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Henry Potkin</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Dennis Barnes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Joseph Borges</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Doughan Gannes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Tenche</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Randall Latham</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Hulme</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Walter Myll</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richard Gilbert</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Steven Pomarie</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Brocke</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bennet Harrye</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>James Stevenson</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Charles Stevenson</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Christopher Lowde</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Jeremie Man</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>James Mason</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>David Salter</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richard Ireland</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Bookener</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Philippes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Randall Mayne</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Bennet Chappell</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richard Sare</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>James Lasie</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Smolkin</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Smart</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Robert</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Evans</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Roger Large</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Humfrey Garden</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Frauncis Whitton</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rowland Griffyn</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Millard</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Twyt</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edwarde Seklemore</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>John Anwike</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Christopher Marshall</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>David Williams</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Nicholas Swabber</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Chipping</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Sylvester Beching</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Vincent Cheyne</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Haunce Walters</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Edward Barecombe</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Thomas Skevelabs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>William Walters</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </appendix>
  <appendix xml:id="mul88">
    <title>The Roanoke Colony, 1587 <footnote xml:id="mul4">
        <para>This Appendix contains an actual list of the individuals who sailed to the Roanoke
          Colony in 1587, as well as the names of children born at the colony. (<emphasis
            role="ital">See</emphasis>
          <citation>Durant, David N., <quote>Raleigh’s Lost Colony</quote>, Appendix I, Atheneum,
            NY: 1981.</citation>)</para>
      </footnote>
    </title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Men</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>John White [Governor]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Roger Bailie [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ananias Dare [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Christopher Cooper [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Stevens [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Sampson [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Dyonis Harvie [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Roger Prat [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>George Howe [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Simon Fernando [Assistant]</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Willes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Brooke</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Cutbert White</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Bright</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Clement Tayler</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Sole</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Cotsmur</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Humfrey Newton</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Colman</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Gramme</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Nicholas Johnson</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Warner</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Anthony Cage</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Jones</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Tydway</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ambrose Viccars</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Edmond English</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Topan</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Berrye</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Berrye</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Spendlove</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Hemmington</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Butler</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Edward Powell</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Burden</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>James Hynde</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Ellis</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Browne</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Michael Myllet</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Smith</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Kemme</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Harris</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Taverner</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Earnest</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Johnson</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Starte</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Darige</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Lucas</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Arnold Archard</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Wright</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Dutton</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Morris Allen</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Waters</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Arthur</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Chapman</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Clement</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Robert Little</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hugh Tayler</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Wildye</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Lewes Wotton</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Michael Bishop</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Browne</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Marke Bennet</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Gibbes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Stilman</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Robert Wilkinson</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Peter Little</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Wyles</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Brian Wyles</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>George Martyn</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hugh Pattenson</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Martyn Sutton</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Farre</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Bridger</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Griffen Jones</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Shaberdge</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>James Lasie</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Cheven</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Hewet</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Berde</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Rufoote</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Richard Tomkins</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Dorrell</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Charles Florrie</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Mylton</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Henry Payne</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Harris</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Nicholes</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Phevens</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Borden</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Scot</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Women</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Elyoner Dare</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Margery Harvie</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Agnes Wood</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Wenefrid Powell</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Joyce Archard</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Jane Jones</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Elizabeth Glane</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Jane Pierce</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Audry Tappan</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Alis Chapman</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Emme Merrimoth</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Colman</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Margaret Lawrence</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Joan Warren</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Jane Mannering</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Rose Payne</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Elizabeth Viccars</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Children</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Sampson</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Robert Ellis</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ambrose Viccars</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Archard</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thomas Humfrey</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Tomas Smart</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>George Howe</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>John Prat</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>William Wythers</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Children Born at the Colony</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Virginia Dare</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Harvye</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Native Peoples (who having been in England returned to the colony)</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Manteo</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Towaye</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </appendix>
  <bibliography>
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="thorpe97" xreflabel="Thorpe 1997">Thorpe, Francis Newton, ed.<emphasis
        role="ital">Charter to Sir Walter Raleigh: 1584,</emphasis> in <quote>The Federal and States
        Constitutions, Colonial Charters, and Other Organic Laws of the States, Territories, and
        Colonies Now or Heretofore Forming the United States of America</quote> (compiled under Act
      of Congress of June 30, 1906). [online]. Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1909.
      The Avalon Project. Co-Dir. William C. Fray &amp; Lisa A. Span. © 1997 [cited 8 Apr
        1998].<link>http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/raleigh.htm</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul94" xreflabel="DeFord 1997">DeFord, Susan. <emphasis role="ital"
        >Tobacco: The Noxious Weed That Built a Nation,</emphasis> Special to <quote>The Washington
        Post</quote> (May 14, 1997) at H01. [online]. © 1997 [cited 29 May 1998].
        <link>http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp~srv/intereact/longterm/horizon/051497/tobacco.htm</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul95" xreflabel="Tobacco"><emphasis role="ital">Part 2. The Story of the
        Arrival and First Uses of Tobacco in Europe,</emphasis> in <quote>The History of
        Tobacco</quote>. [online]. [cited 14 Apr
        1998].<link>http://www.tobacco.co.uk/library/history.html#part2</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul96" xreflabel="Lane">Lane, Ralph. <quote>The Colony at Roanoake —
        1586</quote>. [online]. [cited 13 Apr
        1998].<link>http://www.nationalcenter.inter.net/ColonyofRoanoke.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul97" xreflabel="Prindle 1996a">Prindle, Tara.<emphasis role="ital">Indian
        Corn,</emphasis> excerpted from <quote>Teaching about Thanksgiving</quote>. [online]. Fourth
      World Documentation Project. Native American Technology and Art. © 1996 [cited 14 Apr
        1998].<link>http://www.lib.uconn.edu/NativeTech/cornhusk/cornfwdp.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul98" xreflabel="Prindle 1996b">Prindle, Tara. <quote>Native American
        History of Corn</quote>. [online]. Native American Technology and Art. © 1996 [cited 14 Apr
        1998].<link>http://www.lib.uconn.edu/NativeTech/cornhusk/cornhusk.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul99" xreflabel="Dickerson 1997">Dickerson, George. <quote>Beyond Turkey:
        Corn Shaped History, Cuisines</quote>. [online]. Ed. D’Lyn Ford. New Mexico State University
      College of Agriculture &amp; Home Economics, 11 Nov 1997 [cited 14 Apr
        1998].<link>http://elroy.nmsu.edu/CAHE/press/corn_history1997.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul100" xreflabel="Borio 1954">Borio, Gene.<emphasis role="ital">Smoking in
        England — Elizabethan,</emphasis> excerpted from Alfred H. Dunhill’s <quote>The Gentle Art
        of Smoking</quote>. [online]. Library of Congress catalog card #54-10495 (1954). The Tobacco
      BBS [cited 20 May
      1998].<link>http://www.tobacco.org/History/Elizabethan_smoking.html</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul101" xreflabel="Sellement"><quote>First English Settlement in the New
        World</quote>. [online]. [cited 13 Apr
        1998].<link>http://hal.dcr.state.nc.us/nc/ncsites/English1.htm#First</link>.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="mul-102" xreflabel="ICW-Net 1998"><emphasis role="ital">Virginia
        Dare,</emphasis> in <quote>Tales from the Coast!</quote> [online]. ICW-NET © 1998 [cited 13
      Apr 1998].<link>http://www.outerbanks-nc.com/manteo/history/vadare.htm</link>.</bibliomixed>
  </bibliography>
</article>
